<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Analysis of Volumetric Muscle Loss Injury and Treatments
in the Rodent Lateral Gastrocnemius</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0009-0000-2318-9510</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>Hudson</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Hudson Burke</string-name>

<email>hudsonburke@virginia.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shriver</surname>
<given-names>Sydney</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Sydney Shriver</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>?</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Michael ?</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Xiao</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Xiao Hu</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Christ</surname>
<given-names>George</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>George Christ</string-name>

<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Russell</surname>
<given-names>Shawn</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Shawn Russell</string-name>

<email>sdr2n@virginia.edu</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Virginia</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">hudsonburke@virginia.edu</corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>






</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="abstract">
  <title>1 Abstract</title>
  <p>Volumetric muscle loss (VML) is a debilitating injury involving
  removal of skeletal muscle and resulting in permanent functional
  deficits. This injury is often seen in military personnel from combat
  wounds and in civilian populations from traumatic accidents. While
  significant preclinical research is underway, direct comparisons of
  emerging therapies are rare. This study provides a comprehensive
  biomechanical comparison of multiple treatment strategies for VML in a
  rat model. A 20% by-mass VML defect was created in the lateral
  gastrocnemius (LG) of 48 female Lewis rats, which were divided into
  six groups (n=8 each): No Repair (NR), Tissue-Engineered Muscle Repair
  (TEMR), Healy Hydrogel (HH), Healy Sponge (HS), and combination
  therapies of TEMR with the hydrogel (TEMR+HH) or a keratin gel
  (TEMR+KG). After 24 weeks, we assessed functional recovery using
  motion capture and force plates to determine spatiotemporal
  parameters, joint kinematics, and joint kinetics via OpenSim-based
  inverse dynamics. While no treatment restored full function completely
  in line with the uninjured controls, some groups demonstrated
  improvements, showing trends toward normalized ankle kinematics and
  reduced compensatory kinetic patterns. Others highlighted different
  gait patterns that compensated for a functional loss about the ankle.
  These findings highlight the utility of detailed biomechanical
  analysis in differentiating treatment efficacy for musculoskeletal
  disorders and provide insight into avenues that may better restore
  functional outcomes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>2 Introduction</title>
  <p>Volumetric muscle loss (VML), the traumatic or surgical removal of
  skeletal muscle beyond the point of natural regeneration, results in
  severe, permanent functional impairment
  groganVolumetricMuscleLoss2011. Current clinical treatments for VML,
  such as physical therapy or autologous tissue transfer, have limited
  efficacy in restoring pre-injury muscle strength and function, often
  with the drawback of donor site morbidity
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="Garg%20et%20al.,%202015">Amit
  Aurora et al.
  (<xref alt="2014" rid="ref-AmitAurora-etal-2014" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>);
  (<xref alt="garg?" rid="ref-garg" ref-type="bibr"><bold>garg?</bold></xref>)</ext-link>.
  This clinical gap has spurred significant preclinical research into
  regenerative strategies. These approaches often involve biomaterial
  scaffolds
  (<xref alt="Grasman et al. 2015" rid="ref-Grasman-etal-2015" ref-type="bibr">Grasman
  et al. 2015</xref>;
  <xref alt="Passipieri et al. 2017" rid="ref-Passipieri-etal-2017" ref-type="bibr">Passipieri
  et al. 2017</xref>), injectable hydrogels
  (<xref alt="Wu et al. 2012" rid="ref-Wu-etal-2012" ref-type="bibr">Wu
  et al. 2012</xref>), cell-based therapies, and adjunctive treatments
  like exercise
  (<xref alt="Corona et al. 2017" rid="ref-coronaContributionMincedMuscle2017" ref-type="bibr">Corona
  et al. 2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Dziki et al. 2016" rid="ref-dzikiAcellularBiologicScaffold2016" ref-type="bibr">Dziki
  et al. 2016</xref>). One significant effort has focused on the
  development of a tissue engineered muscle repair (TEMR) construct and
  its use in treating VML in combination with other biomaterials (Corona
  et al., 2012, 2013; Machingal et al., 2011).</p>
  <p>Previous work from this group has demonstrated the efficacy of
  motion capture technology and musculoskeletal modeling for use with
  rodent gait analysis, going beyond the previous standard methodology
  solely examining muscle force generation capacity (Buchner et al.,
  1997; Damiano et al., 2010, 2013; Damiano &amp; Abel, 1998; Topp et
  al., 1993). Dienes (2019) reported changes in gait kinematics in rats
  with VML injuries to the tibialis anterior during treadmill walking.
  Hicks and Dienes (2022) established a normative database for rat gait
  kinematics and kinetics during over-ground walking. They also
  investigated the use of these techniques to analyze These studies have
  established the necessary 3D motion capture and musculoskeletal
  modeling methodologies for evaluating the effectiveness of biomaterial
  constructs as VML treatment strategies.</p>
  <p>The goal of this study is to provide a broad, direct comparison of
  the functional recovery efficacy of different biomaterial treatment
  strategies for VML in a rat hindlimb model using the lateral
  gastrocnemius (LG) muscle. We hypothesized that combination therapies
  providing both a cellular component and a supportive biomaterial would
  yield the greatest restoration of normal gait biomechanics. By
  quantifying changes in spatiotemporal parameters, kinematics, and
  kinetics, we aim to discern which therapeutic strategies most
  effectively mitigate the pathological compensations associated with
  VML and demonstrate the efficacy of rodent gait analysis as a modeling
  platform for various musculoskeletal injuries.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="methods">
  <title>3 Methods</title>
  <sec id="experimental-design">
    <title>3.1 Experimental Design</title>
    <p>Forty-eight 12-week-old female Lewis rats were divided into six
    treatment groups, with eight rats per group. A 20% by-mass
    volumetric muscle loss (VML) injury was created in the left lateral
    gastrocnemius (LG) muscle of each animal. The first group was a
    <italic>No Repair (NR)</italic> control, where the injury site was
    left empty. The second group received a <italic>Tissue-Engineered
    Muscle Repair (TEMR)</italic>, which involved filling the site with
    a cell-seeded bioscaffold. The third and fourth groups received
    acellular treatments, consisting of either a pro-regenerative
    <italic>Healy Hydrogel (HH)</italic> or a porous collagen
    <italic>Healy Sponge (HS)</italic>. The final two groups received
    combination treatments: one group was given the <italic>TEMR
    construct with the Healy Hydrogel (TEMR+HH)</italic>, and the other
    received the <italic>TEMR construct with an acellular keratin gel
    (TEMR+KG)</italic>. Functional assessment was performed 24 weeks
    post-surgery and each group was compared to the group that received
    no repair to clarify trends in recovery or decline. A previously
    collected dataset of 32 animals was used as the
    <italic>Control</italic> group.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="animal-care-and-surgical-procedures">
    <title>3.2 Animal Care and Surgical Procedures</title>
    <p>All animal procedures were approved by the University of Virginia
    Animal Care and Use Committee, conducted in compliance with the
    <italic>Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic> ,
    the Animal Welfare Act, and the Implementing Animal Welfare
    Regulations. Lewis Rats (Charles River Laboratories) were
    pair-housed in a vivarium accredited by the American Association for
    the Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care with ad libitum access
    to food and water.</p>
    <p>The VML injury surgery was performed in accordance with the
    procedure outlined in Merritt et al. (2010). The LG was exposed and
    a 20% distal portion was excised by mass. The assigned repair
    material was then implanted into the defect following methodologies
    in the respective literature (Corona et al., 2012, 2013; Machingal
    et al., 2011). No repair material was implanted in the no repair
    (NR) group. The overlying fascia was closed with 6-0 vicryl sutures,
    and the skin was closed with 5-0 prolene using interrupted sutures
    with skin glue over top to reduce the risk of reopening the
    incision.</p>
    <p>Prior to surgery, slow-release buprenorphine was administered
    (0.1 mg/kg, subcutaneously). All surgical procedures along with
    shaving and motion capture marker placement were performed under
    continuous isoflurane anesthesia inhalation (1.5–2.5%). The depth of
    anesthesia was monitored by the response of the animal to a slight
    toe pinch, where the lack of response was considered the surgical
    plane of anesthesia. A heated water perfusion system was utilized
    for core temperature maintenance. Post-operative analgesia was
    provided with quick-release buprenorphine (0.1 mg/kg,
    subcutaneously) at 36 and 48 hours. No animal required additional
    analgesia after 48 hours post-surgery as determined by veterinary
    staff that monitored for pain and distress.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="motion-capture-and-gait-analysis">
    <title>3.3 Motion Capture and Gait Analysis</title>
    <p>After 24 weeks to allow for injury progression or healing, gait
    data was collected for each rat in the treatment groups. Reflective
    markers were adhered to bony landmarks on the pelvis and joint
    locations on the hindlimb based on the set described by Johnson et
    al. (2008) and utilized in previous studies by this group (Dienes
    2019, 2022). Marker locations were: (1) L6 vertebra, (2) 5th caudal
    vertebra, (3-4) left and right anterior iliac crests, (5-6) left and
    right greater trochanter of the femur, (7-8) left and right lateral
    femoral epicondyle, (9-10) left and right lateral malleolus, and
    (11-12) left and right lateral aspect of the distal end of the 5th
    metatarsal. After an acclimation period, rats walked along an
    instrumented walkway while motion was captured with a seven-camera
    Vicon system recording marker data at 200Hz and synchronized with
    four in-ground ATI six-axis force transducers recording ground
    reaction forces at 1000 Hz. A minimum of three successful trials
    wherein one complete steady-state gait cycle, defined from foot
    strike to foot strike, per hindlimb without overlap on a force plate
    during stance phase were collected for each rat at each time
    point.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="gait-modeling-and-statistical-analysis">
    <title>3.4 Gait Modeling and Statistical Analysis</title>
    <p>Marker trajectories and ground reaction force data were filtered
    using a 4th order, low-pass, Butterworth filter (cutoff frequencies
    of 15 Hz and 100 Hz, respectively). For each rat, a subject specific
    OpenSim model of the hindlimbs was generated from limb measurements
    and previously acquired limb anthropometrics (Hicks and Dienes et
    al., 2022). OpenSim’s inverse kinematic and inverse dynamic tools
    were used to compute hindlimb joint angles and joint moments.
    Reported data corresponds to one gait cycle, with the stance and
    swing phase of the right stride reported independently to minimize
    the effects of phasing caused by velocity differences. Moments were
    normalized to total body mass multiplied by the total length as is
    common practice for kinetic analysis in biomechanics (Winters 2009).
    Limitations to this normalization strategy will be covered in the
    Discussion section. Spatiotemporal parameters (STPs) were calculated
    in Vicon Nexus using standard definitions as presented in Huxley et
    al(). At the 24-week endpoint, STPs were compared to No Repair
    dataset using unpaired t-tests. For time-series kinematic and
    kinetic data, Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM) with unpaired
    t-tests was used to identify regional significant differences across
    the gait cycle between groups indicated by highlighted vertical
    rectangles
    (<xref alt="Pataky et al. 2016" rid="ref-patakyRegionofinterestAnalysesOnedimensional2016" ref-type="bibr">Pataky
    et al. 2016</xref>). A red highlighted region indicates significant
    difference compared to No Repair, and a black highlighted region
    indicates significant difference compared to Control. Statistical
    significance was set at α=0.05.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="results">
  <title>4 Results</title>
  <sec id="spatiotemporal-parameters">
    <title>4.1 Spatiotemporal Parameters</title>
    <p>Stride length, step width, and velocity are normalized by leg
    length calculated by summing the femur and tibia lengths.</p>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/STP_table.png" />
    <p><italic>^, <sup></sup>, <sup></sup>^ indicates p &lt; 0.05, 0.01,
    0Master’s.001 respectively compared to NR</italic></p>
    <p><italic>*, **, *** indicates p &lt; 0.05, 0.01, 0.001
    respectively compared to Control</italic></p>
    <p>The No Repair group had a significantly narrower step width and
    decreased stance percentage compared to the control group. This
    narrower step width was reflected in nearly every other treatment
    except the TEMR+HH group. All groups that received some form of TEMR
    treatment moved significantly slower compared to both the Control
    and No Repair groups. This was coupled with significant increases in
    stance percentages and decreases in stride lengths compared to the
    Control group.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="kinematics-and-kinetics">
    <title>4.2 Kinematics and Kinetics</title>
    <sec id="no-repair-nr">
      <title>4.2.1 No Repair (NR)</title>
      <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/NR_kinematics.png" />
      <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/NR_kinetics.png" /></p>
      <p>The primary differences seen in the injured subjects compared
      to the control dataset were an increased ankle dorsiflexion angle
      during mid-stance coupled with increases in the knee extension and
      hip internal rotation moments. These changes suggest that to
      compensate for the loss of plantarflexor function, the animals are
      adopting a gait strategy that reduces the demand on the ankle
      joint by increasing dorsiflexion and utilizing more proximal
      musculature to generate the necessary extension moments at the
      knee and hip. Effective therapies would be expected to mitigate
      these compensations and restore more normal kinematic and kinetic
      patterns.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="healy-hydrogel-hh">
      <title>4.2.2 Healy Hydrogel (HH)</title>
      <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/HH_kinematics.png" />
      <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/HH_kinetics.png" /></p>
      <p>The Healy Hydrogel group demonstrated very similar kinematic
      and kinetic patterns to the No Repair group, with increased ankle
      dorsiflexion during mid-stance and elevated knee extension and hip
      internal rotation moments. Significance was also seen in some
      other kinematic measures, but this is likely a result of
      variability in marker placement. This suggests that the hydrogel
      alone did not provide sufficient functional recovery to alter the
      compensatory gait strategies observed in the No Repair group.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="healy-sponge-hs">
      <title>4.2.3 Healy Sponge (HS)</title>
      <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/HS_kinematics.png" />
      <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/HS_kinetics.png" /></p>
      <p>The Healy Sponge group exhibited kinematic and kinetic patterns
      more similar to the Control group compared to the No Repair and
      Healy Hydrogel groups. While some significant difference remained
      in the knee extension moment, the curve shifted away from the
      trajectory seen in the No Repair group and towards the Control
      group, and the overall patterns suggested a trend toward
      normalization of gait mechanics. The difference in ankle
      dorsiflexion angle did not reach the level of significance
      compared to either the Control or No Repair groups, but visual
      inspection of the curves suggests it is still closer to the No
      Repair values, and the lack of significance is more likely a
      result of a higher variance. This indicates that the sponge may
      have provided a more conducive environment for muscle regeneration
      or functional compensation compared to the hydrogel.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="tissue-engineered-muscle-repair-combination-therapies">
      <title>4.2.4 Tissue-Engineered Muscle Repair Combination
      Therapies</title>
      <p>Many of the TEMR groups exhibited similar patterns and will be
      analyzed together.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="tissue-engineered-muscle-repair-temr">
      <title>4.2.5 Tissue-Engineered Muscle Repair (TEMR)</title>
      <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/TEMR_kinematics.png" />
      <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/TEMR_kinetics.png" /></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="temr-and-hydrogel-temrhh">
      <title>4.2.6 TEMR and Hydrogel (TEMR+HH)</title>
      <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/TEMR_HH_kinematics.png" />
      <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/TEMR_HH_kinetics.png" /></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="temr-and-keratin-gel-temrkg">
      <title>4.2.7 TEMR and Keratin Gel (TEMR+KG)</title>
      <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/TEMR_KG_kinematics.png" />
      <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/TEMR_KG_kinetics.png" /></p>
      <p>Kinematically, the ankle dorsiflexion angle is still
      significantly elevated in mid-stance compared to Control. The
      kinetic profile across all three TEMR groups is similar, with
      decreased knee extension moment during stance compared to the No
      Repair group but still significantly greater than the Control
      group. Similarly, the hip internal rotation moments are
      significantly greater than Control in mid-stance, akin to the No
      Repair group. A unique adaptation that surfaces in the TEMR groups
      is a decrease in ankle plantarflexion moment compared to both the
      Control and No Repair groups during mid-stance. These findings
      suggest that while the TEMR treatments may not fully restore
      normal gait mechanics, they do introduce unique compensatory
      strategies, particularly at the ankle joint.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="discussion">
  <title>5 Discussion</title>
  <sec id="summary-of-findings">
    <title>5.1 Summary of Findings</title>
    <p>This study provides a comprehensive biomechanical analysis of
    various treatment strategies for volumetric muscle loss (VML) in a
    rat model. The No Repair group exhibited significant compensatory
    gait adaptations, including increased ankle dorsiflexion and
    elevated knee and hip moments, indicative of the functional deficits
    caused by VML. This pattern continued in treatment groups, though to
    lesser extent, and likely represents a more flat-footed posture
    during stance to be able to transfer more powere to the ground with
    the knee. The Healy Hydrogel treatment did not significantly alter
    these compensatory patterns, suggesting limited functional recovery.
    In contrast, the Healy Sponge treatment showed trends toward
    normalization of gait mechanics, indicating a more favorable
    environment for muscle regeneration or compensation. The TEMR-based
    treatments, while not fully restoring normal gait mechanics,
    introduced unique compensatory strategies, particularly at the ankle
    joint, highlighting their potential to mitigate some functional
    deficits associated with VML.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="limitations-and-future-directions">
    <title>5.2 Limitations and Future Directions</title>
    <p>In this study, joint moments were normalized to body mass
    multiplied by total length, a common approach to account for size
    differences among subjects and facilitate comparison across groups.
    However, this normalization method has limitations as it is based on
    geometric scaling assumptions that may not adequately reflect rodent
    limb growth over time. This analysis is limited by the lack of
    age-matched controls that would provide a more direct comparison
    between pathological gait adaptation and normative gait patterns.
    Examining uninjured rodent gait patterns over time would also
    provide an insight into potential normalization strategies. From a
    small subset of uninjured rats, we noticed that there may be a
    disproportionate growth in the tibia length compared to the femur
    which could impact the moment arms seen at different joints. This
    study provides a valuable biomechanical analysis of several
    different VML repairs at a single time point. A key future direction
    is a longitudinal analysis to track the evolution of these gait
    adaptations over the entire 24-week period, which would reveal the
    time-dependent aspects of recovery and delineate the progression of
    pathological compensation strategies. Additionally, while the
    inverse dynamics analysis reveals net joint moments, it falls short
    of partitioning these into individual muscle force contributions.
    Future work using advanced musculoskeletal modeling techniques, such
    as computed muscle control, could estimate these forces and provide
    deeper insight into neuromuscular compensation patterns.
    Furthermore, expansion of the model to include the front limbs could
    uncover further ways that the rats compensate for musculoskeletal
    deficiencies. Finally, correlating these functional outcomes with
    histological and molecular analyses of the repair tissue would
    delineate the biological mechanisms that contribute to the
    distinction between successful and unsuccessful treatments.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusion">
  <title>6 Conclusion</title>
  <p>Volumetric muscle loss causes functional impairments that are not
  adequately addressed by current clinical practice. This study provides
  a broad comparison of the long-term functional efficacy of several
  preclinical regenerative strategies. We found that while no treatment
  achieved a full return to uninjured function, therapies incorporating
  a specific sponge material produced modest but significant trends
  toward functional healing, demonstrating mitigated pathological gait
  compensations. This work emphasizes the utility and importance of
  detailed biomechanical assessment in evaluating VML treatments and
  highlights the potential of biomaterials to enhance regenerative
  outcomes.</p>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title></title>
  <ref id="ref-patakyRegionofinterestAnalysesOnedimensional2016">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Pataky</surname><given-names>Todd</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Vanrenterghem</surname><given-names>Jos</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Region-of-interest analyses of onedimensional biomechanical trajectories: Bridging 0D and 1D theory, augmenting statistical power</article-title>
      <source>PeerJ</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016-11">2016</year><month>11</month>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2652</pub-id>
      <fpage>e2652</fpage>
      <lpage></lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Wu-etal-2012">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Xiaowu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>Benjamin T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiaoyu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>Thomas J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A standardized rat model of volumetric muscle loss injury for the development of tissue engineering therapies</article-title>
      <source>BioResearch Open Access</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2012-12">2012</year><month>12</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-10-02">2024</year><month>10</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <issn>2164-7844</issn>
      <uri>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3559228/</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/biores.2012.0271</pub-id>
      <fpage>280</fpage>
      <lpage>290</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Passipieri-etal-2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Passipieri</surname><given-names>Juliana A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Hannah B.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Siriwardane</surname><given-names>Mevan</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ellenburg</surname><given-names>Mary D.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Vadhavkar</surname><given-names>Manasi</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>Justin M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Tomblyn</surname><given-names>Seth</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>Luke</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>George J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Keratin hydrogel enhances in vivo skeletal muscle function in a rat model of volumetric muscle loss.</article-title>
      <source>Tissue Engineering Part A</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017-06-01">2017</year><month>06</month><day>01</day>
      <volume>23</volume>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.tea.2016.0458</pub-id>
      <fpage>556</fpage>
      <lpage>571</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Grasman-etal-2015">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Grasman</surname><given-names>Jonathan M.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Zayas</surname><given-names>Michelle J.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>Raymond L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Pins</surname><given-names>George D.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Biomimetic scaffolds for regeneration of volumetric muscle loss in skeletal muscle injuries.</article-title>
      <source>Acta Biomaterialia</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2015-10-01">2015</year><month>10</month><day>01</day>
      <volume>25</volume>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2015.07.038</pub-id>
      <fpage>2</fpage>
      <lpage>15</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-coronaContributionMincedMuscle2017">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>Benjamin T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>Beth E. P.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>Catherine L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Greising</surname><given-names>Sarah M.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Contribution of minced muscle graft progenitor cells to muscle fiber formation after volumetric muscle loss injury in wild-type and immune deficient mice.</article-title>
      <source>Physiological Reports</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017-04">2017</year><month>04</month>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14814/phy2.13249</pub-id>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28400501</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-dzikiAcellularBiologicScaffold2016">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Dziki</surname><given-names>Jenna</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Badylak</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Yabroudi</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Sicari</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Ambrosio</surname><given-names>Fabrisia</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Stearns</surname><given-names>Kristen</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>Neill</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Wyse</surname><given-names>Aaron</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Boninger</surname><given-names>Michael L.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Elke H. P.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>J. Peter</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>An acellular biologic scaffold treatment for volumetric muscle loss: Results of a 13-patient cohort study</article-title>
      <source>npj Regenerative Medicine</source>
      <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2016-07">2016</year><month>07</month>
      <date-in-citation content-type="access-date"><year iso-8601-date="2024-10-02">2024</year><month>10</month><day>02</day></date-in-citation>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <issn>2057-3995</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npjregenmed.2016.8</pub-id>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>12</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-AmitAurora-etal-2014">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Amit Aurora</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Aurora</surname><given-names>Amit</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Koyal Garg</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>Koyal</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Benjamin T. Corona</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>Benjamin T.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>James Walters</surname></name>
        <name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>Thomas J.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Physical rehabilitation improves muscle function following volumetric muscle loss injury</article-title>
      <source>Sports Medicine, Arthroscopy, Rehabilitation, Therapy &amp; Technology</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2014-12-19">2014</year><month>12</month><day>19</day>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2052-1847-6-41</pub-id>
      <fpage>41</fpage>
      <lpage>41</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>



</article>